Thank you so much for coming later in
the week here.
Uh
I'm Matt.
I'm the CEO and founder of Ref.
The problem we work on at Ref is one you
might be familiar with where individual
engineers are going really fast with AI,
but the team as a whole is not. And
we're working to help close that gap.
What I'm going to be talking about today
is that is what happens when your whole
team gets 10 times faster.
All the things that don't go well.
And my goal is to give you a blueprint
for how to get get through those issues.
Uh and have the whole team move
faster together.
The way I want to accomplish that is
first
talk about those issues, define some
terms.
Then we'll talk about how did we get
here?
Where are we at now?
Um and we'll use that to
triangulate on some solutions. We'll
start high level and we'll work down to
get more and more practical until we
leave with a couple of things you can
leave here and do immediately.
Um how's that sound? I need thumbs up.
All right, awesome. Great, that was
great. Uh
All right, so let's get into it.
These are some of the problems you might
be experiencing right now.
Uh these are these are problems that
affect individuals and are actually
magnified
at the team level once the entire team
starts experiencing them.
The first one,
too many PRs to merge. This is the like
classic first problem you hit when you
start adopting AI as an engineer. You're
like, "Great, I'm shipping stuff." And
you push up those PRs and you're like,
"There's no way I can merge all these."
Uh and this is obviously magnified when
the whole team does this.
Merge conflicts, merge queue breaks
down,
things get bad.
The second problem is that you're moving
in many directions at once.
This is also both individual and a team
problem. Individually, this is where you
have a bunch of agents doing different
things. You're trying to remember who's
doing what
and your brain gets fried.
At the organizational level, this is
your engineers
picking up things and running in a
certain direction. Another engineer is
running over here.
Maybe some are bumping into each other
and you're you're not moving cohesively
with focus because you're just sprinting
in all sorts of directions.
The third problem you might be
experiencing is declaring agent
bankruptcy. This is a a common pattern I
see engineers get into where
you know, you're cranking. You have like
your 12 terminals open. You're like at
the end of the day you're like, "Yeah, I
did a lot of work." You step away from
your laptop.
Uh
spend time with your friends and family.
Next morning you come back and it's like
walking into just a room of strangers.
Like, who are these people? What are
they doing here? But like
no problem. They're agents so you just
like
get rid of them and start over again.
The problem though is you know, it feels
like you're doing a lot of work but
you're doing the same work
and you're spending tokens twice. You're
doing the same problems over over again.
And if you think about that
organizationally, that's your team not
being efficient with both their time and
their their token resources.
Problem four though is actually the most
important one.
It's critical decisions being made by
agents. Once you have agents
doing a lot of your work,
if if you as an engineer are letting an
agent make a critical decision, you are
seeding control of your code. You are no
longer the owner of that code. The agent
is.
And if you imagine that at scale at your
company, if the engineers across your
team are you know, giving up ownership
of the code, you no longer own the
product.
These are a bunch of problems you might
be experiencing at different degrees
at different days. Uh
The way I like bundle it up is into this
term velocity sickness.
This is uh
the stress caused by sudden output
increases thanks to AI. Um it affects
individuals or teams.
Um and the result is output without
impact. So, this is that feeling of like
we're moving really fast. This should
feel great. This should feel awesome,
but for some reason it doesn't feel
awesome. We're not having the like the
things you expect to be happening are
not happening. Um despite this feeling
of being so productive.
So, that's to define that term, but I
want to tell uh a little story.
Uh
my talk is happening now.
I want to tell a little story
about somebody like to make this very
real.
Um
This is a story about somebody uh who's
actually not an engineer, but I think it
parallels our engineering workflows a
lot. I Part of my job is I get to go,
find, and talk to people who are really
pushing the forefront and try and learn
from them. And I love that part of it.
And so, this is somebody and I'm I'm
talking through their identical
workflows.
Um and this is somebody who writes a
newsletter, and
their workflow is around how do I I have
my ideas and then they're doing research
and exploration and then uh like
cohesion between those ideas and
editorial to make sure it's in their
voice. And they're they're walking me
through their system for how they they
manage this whole pipeline um and really
scale out their
their efficacy. And this is like very
very much not slop. This is somebody who
has is using agents to amplify their own
voice uh in a way that's like very
impressive. I'm like, "Wow, that's that
is so cool. I'm I'm like
I'm soaking it in." Uh
And then they're like, "Yeah, I'm
basically writing a book every week."
And I'm like, "Oh,
okay. Is like is your audience reading a
book every week?"
And they're like, "No, they're probably
not." Right? They're not. They're
they're This is a person who's
writing a lot, but those pages that
they're writing
are going unread. Um
I think that's part of this experience
of velocity sickness is we're we're
building things that are not
mattering for the people we want them to
matter for, the people we're trying to
reach. Uh So, what we Instead of unread
pages,
um what we want is we want to write
words that matter. We want to write
words that connect with people.
Um and the parallel to us as like
software builders and product builders
is is that
we want to write we want to build
products that connect with people. We
want We want to build products that
change the way people live and work and
make their lives better. And we have
more ability to do that than ever with
AI.
But we have this like feeling of
velocity sickness where we're It feels
like we should be doing that, but it's
not quite landing.
So, let's talk about how we got here.
Um
This is what the software engineering
process used to look like before AI.
We'd do some planning up front.
We'd sit down and build. We'd implement.
It'd be It'd be iterative. We'd be
exploring. But largely we're sitting
down building
in isolation, implementing something.
And at the end we sort of polish it up
and ship it out the door. And this was
great. We all knew how to do this. We
had a lot of systems for this. Uh
And it was good. And then AI came along.
Um
But
at this time our our tools were built
for this. Like all all our history of
coding tools were built for this style
of work.
Um our IDE, our workhorse, um it was
built for implementation and polish to
be done by an individual, to be heads
down building as a software engineer
writing code.
Um That's what That's a tool built for
how we used to work.
Um so, let's look at how how we work
now.
Our work looks a lot more like this.
Where you do some planning up front. You
start thinking about what am I trying to
do here? You take this idea in your head
and start to flesh it out.
Um At some point an agent takes that
idea and like implements it. This is
like arguably should not even be on this
slide cuz it's not our human work
anymore. It's done by the agent. Um
and then in the end we do some polishing
where we take back that thing the agent
has made for us and we like hold it in
our hands and we say, is this is this
what I wanted? Um
This is a very different shape of work.
Right? We're no longer doing this like
heads down building.
These are the two uh
creative and collaborative parts of our
work as engineers. This is where we like
express our craft as an engineer. And
the one that's most different is the the
planning stage. So, I want to zoom in on
that just a little bit.
Uh that's the like exploratory,
creative, collaborative part where we're
we're thinking about like I have this
vague idea.
I have this complex system. I need to
understand the contours of this system,
apply this idea, and like
really understand it. And I need to pull
out what's relevant and express my taste
as an engineer. As to like, where do I
want this system to go?
Um
This is the kind of work that uh
that's creative and and needs to be done
together. I think the the shape of
engineering teams and product teams is
changing with AI.
But we're always going to have this
thing where we have a group of people
responsible for managing a complex
system and it's sort of deciding the
future of that system. And that's this
planning work. And so, we're
we're starting to see some of the hints
of like, okay, we had tools built for a
certain type of work. Our work looks
different now.
Um Let's start to see think about that a
little bit more.
So, uh we used to have the IDE as our
main tool. It was used for
implementation.
But now we're doing this different kind
of work. So, at the very high level, we
can start to think about solutions like,
okay, we have a tool built for this type
of work. We have a new type of work.
Let's think about
you know, what this new layer of our
work is. This This is the decision
layer. This is where we're thinking
through
what are the key decisions, doing that
like craft of engineering, um and
expressing our taste as engineers,
ultimately a different thing than
implementation.
And it
it's a different gear as an engineer.
The skill now is what gear am I in? Am I
using the appropriate tools for the gear
that I'm what I'm trying to accomplish
right now.
So let's think about what a tool built
for the decision layer would look like.
It'd be a tool built for docs
and not chat. And there's that's like a
short sentence. There's a lot to unpack
here though. So I'm going to spend a lot
of time on this slide.
The problem with chats
is that they are
the relic of building for
implementation. So they're
they're default isolated and ephemeral
and and brain off.
They're they're made to build things and
get stuff done. And that's not really
the same type of work we're doing
at the decision layer. We're doing this
creative exploratory work. So being in
this isolated environment where I'm
working with an agent, maybe I start
with my vague idea and I'm exploring it
and asking questions, but decisions are
being made in that like that chat that
are are not shared with my team
that are
going to disappear as as long I'm going
to
result in some code being output where
those important decisions are not being
made clear and shared with the team. And
you're also in this mode where the agent
saying
Okay, this is what I want to do. Is is
that okay? Let's go. Or or sometimes
it'll say it'll ask you a question and
it'll be like
you know, this is the recommended option
and then you're like, great. I don't
even think about this. I'll just hit
that one and we keep going.
Docs start to solve this problem. So
when you're if you center your work
around
working in docs
they're meant to be bring forward the
key decisions. This is this is what our
work is now. Our work now is
figure out what decisions matter and
then make those decisions
and then get out of the way while the
agents fill in the rest.
Working in Docs is the the classic way
we would create alignment.
If you were If you think back to being a
manager or
a lead on a team before AI, if your team
was having struggling with alignment,
you would not tell them like, "Let's go
all work in Slack DMs. Let's like go
direct message each other." You'd say,
"Let's
like bring forward key decisions, align
on them, spend time on these, like find
a way that we can really spend time
getting our decisions right."
So, there are two things you might be
thinking looking at this that are not
what I'm talking about here. The first
one is plan mode. That's a great tool.
The other one is like full-on factory
spectrum and development. That's a great
tool, too. I'm talking about something
in the middle.
Plan mode is great, but it's largely
a a rich chat message where the agent is
saying, "Hey, here's a like better
visualization of what I'm trying to
express to you." Yeah, that's great.
But it's still in this isolated
ephemeral environment.
And what I'm suggesting is something
more more durable,
more shared, more long-lived that you
and your team are spending time on.
Similarly, the spectrum and development
where we just define the behaviors, we
operate at the like product level,
is a little far away from the
engineering reality.
The engineering reality is that I need
to understand my system and have a tool
that
like helps me understand that system and
lay out those key decisions in a in a
technical sense. The way I like to
conceptualize this is as the portal to
the software system, where you are like
Tony Stark and you're like, "Show me
what matters." And you're like, "I'm
working on this. Pull out the bits that
are relevant." And AI is amazing at
finding things that are related to other
things, helping you find what's what's
relevant and lay them out on the table
in front of you. Organize the pieces in
the way you want to represent how you
want the system to grow.
But the big conceptual flip here is
actually that we're pulling out the
state. So, when you're living and
working in a
a long-lived session with an agent,
there's this implicit context being
built up like over that work, and that's
great. Um
But there's you're also doing actions
and it's it's not shared. What you want
is to separate the
the agent as the action and the doc as
the state. And so, you can spawn new
agents that have the same context or
starting from the same place
that are able to collaborate and work on
the same
same
piece of context and state. You're
ultimately doing context engineering in
this doc, so that every agent is largely
stateless and starts from this place um
the same place. And what that gives you
is your team and yourself can look into
this and understand
what actually is in here. What are the
decisions that are being made um
and have a a clear understanding of what
the key decisions are.
So, this is a a different way of working
where your your core atom of your work
is a doc rather than a chat. Um
What happens when you actually start to
implement this?
Well, the first thing we see happen
actually is that people start to plan
and then not implement their plan.
Uh and this is actually like a really
good sign.
Because what that means is they're
thinking through ideas. They're saying,
"I have this idea. Let me explore it.
Let me start to flesh it out. Like I
have this vague thought. Don't just give
me some code. Don't go off and like
build it for me, but let me help help me
understand the idea that I'm talking
about. Um
And then they have a bunch of these and
then some of them are getting built and
some of them aren't. So, that means
they're prioritizing the ideas that
after they've explored them
are the ones that are worth building and
and going in this to the next step with.
Um One way I like to frame this is that
you're you're shifting from code
velocity
to idea velocity. So,
going back to our
our problem statement like how are we
dealing with velocity sickness? The
velocity sickness is we're shipping too
much code that's not going anywhere. The
solution
is to shift that velocity to ideas so
that rather than
you know, getting stuck in prototype
gravity where we we build something and
we're so excited to just ship that thing
and we're going down like one path of
the idea maze,
we can now like more more effectively
explore that whole maze and find that
gold that's around the corner.
Um
and and really
impact the people we're trying to help.
Um
So, let's go back. Here are those
problems, those velocity sickness
problems I talked about the beginning.
Let's see how this starts to address
those.
First,
too many PRs.
We've moved the the review point earlier
into the process. So, we're aligning on
the key decisions up front.
That means the code review is easier
because the hardest part of any code
review is,
you know, what actually matters here.
That's the first step is like, "Hmm,
what do I care about here?"
If you move that earlier, we've aligned
on that, the code review becomes much
simpler.
Number two, moving in too many
directions. Again, we're aligning early
as a team and individually, I'm like
understanding what I'm working on across
many agents. If I'm working on a large
thing,
I've I've understood it initially. So,
as a team, we're sharing these plans and
we're aligning. This is what we're
trying to build and it's easy before
someone has spent
even a day in AI going deep on some idea
building a prototype, we can talk about
it early and make sure we're aligned on
where we actually taking the system.
Um declaring agent bankruptcy is just
not a thing because you've made your
agent stateless. So,
the result of their work is in the
stock. If you need to rebuild your human
context,
you just read the doc. Now, you
understand the state of this project and
you can pick up from there.
And the most important one,
humans own the decisions. Like, that's
what we're solving for. Humans need to
own the decisions.
That's how we retain ownership of our
software and our products
and make it like a true expression of
what we're trying to create in the
world.
There are also some other benefits. So,
when you have this state extracted and
you're working from a shared context,
you get more parallel agents. It's
easier to work with parallel agents.
Uh you get this durable decision log.
So, something uh that's really powerful.
I think a lot of people are thinking
about how do we capture all the
decisions going into these sessions?
A really great solution to that is let's
pull out all the decisions up front and
agree to them and put them in a place
that's durable so that we don't have to
have like some LLM summarizing it and
maybe picking the wrong things later on.
We want to bring that forward so we can
save it and refer to it later.
Um and then my favorite one um
is actually more collaboration.
Like
this process, we want we're doing more
work that is creative,
which means we should be collaborating
more as engineers. I think the future of
engineering is multiplayer.
It's going to be multi multiplayer by
default sooner than we think.
Um
and it's more important than ever
because we're in this moment with AI
where everything's moving faster than
ever. There's a pressure like everyone's
company feels existential, small or big.
You need to deliver. And the way we get
through that as humans is by working
together. And we need tools that help us
do that.
So, here are three
concrete things you can leave this room
and do right now.
The first one is to think of your work
in terms of planning and polish.
So, recognizing that there are two gears
I'm working in. There's no longer this
one focus of implementation. There's uh
plan and then polish.
Um and notice when you're in a single
session and
you're doing both of these in one
session. Notice when you drift from the
planning phase into the polish phase and
is your tool serving you for what you're
trying to do at that moment?
Uh
number two is to start to treat your
plan as a portal to the software system.
So, really treating it as this powerful,
malleable tool to say like, what matters
to to me for what I'm working on right
now?
Um and asking it to show that to you so
that you can make the best decisions
possible.
And number three is share a plan. Like,
don't just
you know, write the plan, give it to
your agent, and have them implement it.
Give it to someone on your team. This is
like, I feel like very unnatural for a
lot of people. We always we we think we
know what's going on.
But, it's always valuable. You have
smart teammates. They have
great context in their heads. You should
tap into that. They will give you good
feedback.
Uh it's a really valuable thing to do.
That's my talk. I'm Matt. Um I'm the CEO
of Ref. If you want to talk about any of
this stuff, this has all my like
connection information. Ref is a tool
built for the decision layer.
Uh we work with all of your existing
implementation tools.
Um if you want to see a demo, come you
can come by our booth or just see me out
there.
Uh and I'd love to talk about this
stuff, so come say hi.
Thanks.